<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-li-pce-sr-bidir-path-07" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SR Bidirectional Association in PCEP">PCEP Extensions for
    Associated Bidirectional Segment Routing (SR) Paths</title>

    <author fullname="Cheng Li" initials="C." surname="Li">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengli13@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach(Guoyi) Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Mach.chen@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Weiqiang Cheng" initials="W." surname="Cheng">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>chengweiqiang@chinamobile.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rakesh Gandhi" initials="R." surname="Gandhi">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>rgandhi@cisco.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Quan Xiong" initials="Q." surname="Xiong">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>xiong.quan@zte.com.cn</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="6" month="February" year="2020"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>PCE Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) provides
      mechanisms for Path Computation Elements (PCEs) to perform path
      computations in response to Path Computation Clients (PCCs) requests.
      The Stateful PCE extensions allow stateful control of Multiprotocol
      Label Switching (MPLS) Traffic Engineering (TE) Label Switched Paths
      (LSPs) using PCEP. Furthermore, PCEP can be used for computing paths in
      Segment Routing (SR) TE networks.</t>

      <t>This document defines PCEP extensions for grouping two reverse
      unidirectional SR Paths into an Associated Bidirectional SR Path when
      using a Stateful PCE for both PCE-Initiated and PCC-Initiated LSPs as
      well as when using a Stateless PCE.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Segment routing (SR) <xref target="RFC8402"/> leverages the source
      routing and tunneling paradigms. SR supports to steer packets into an
      explicit forwarding path at the ingress node.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC5440"/> describes the Path Computation Element (PCE)
      Communication Protocol (PCEP). PCEP enables the communication between a
      Path Computation Client (PCC) and a PCE, or between PCE and PCE, for the
      purpose of computation of Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) as well
      as Generalized MPLS (GMPLS) Traffic Engineering Label Switched Path (TE
      LSP) characteristics.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8231"/> specifies a set of extensions to PCEP to
      enable stateful control of TE LSPs within and across PCEP sessions in
      compliance with <xref target="RFC4657"/>. It includes mechanisms to
      effect LSP State Synchronization between PCCs and PCEs, delegation of
      control over LSPs to PCEs, and PCE control of timing and sequence of
      path computations within and across PCEP sessions. The model of
      operation where LSPs are initiated from the PCE is described in <xref
      target="RFC8281"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> specifies extensions to
      the Path Computation Element Protocol (PCEP) <xref target="RFC5440"/>
      for SR networks, that allow a stateful PCE to compute and initiate SR-TE
      paths, as well as a PCC to request, report or delegate SR Paths.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> introduces a generic
      mechanism to create a grouping of LSPs which can then be used to define
      associations between a set of LSPs and/or a set of attributes, for
      example primary and secondary LSP associations, and is equally
      applicable to the active and passive modes of a Stateful PCE <xref
      target="RFC8231"/> or a stateless PCE <xref target="RFC5440"/>.</t>

      <t>Currently, SR networks only support unidirectional paths. However,
      bidirectional SR Paths are required in some networks, for example, in
      mobile backhaul transport networks. The requirement of bidirectional SR
      Path is specified in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> defines PCEP
      extensions for grouping two reverse unidirectional MPLS TE LSPs into an
      Associated Bidirectional LSP when using a Stateful PCE for both
      PCE-Initiated and PCC-Initiated LSPs as well as when using a Stateless
      PCE.</t>

      <t>This document extends the bidirectional association to segment
      routing by specifying PCEP extensions for grouping two reverse
      unidirectional SR Paths into a bidirectional SR Path.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> specifies the
      Double-sided Bidirectional LSP Association procedure, where the PCE
      creates the association and provisions at both endpoints, the RSVP-TE
      does the signaling to the egress the status of the forward LSP and the
      ingress about the reverse LSP. Thus, the both endpoints learn the
      reverse LSPs forming the bidirectional LSP association. In case of SR,
      to support the bidirectional path use-case, this is done using the PCEP
      protocol. This is done so that both endpoints are aware of the the
      unidirectional SR Path, as well as the status and other SR path related
      information.</t>

      <t/>

      <t><xref target="I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment"/> defines a procedure for
      Path Segment Identifier (PSID) in PCEP for SR using PATH-SEGMENT TLV.
      The PSID can be a Path Segment Identifier in SR-MPLS <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-spring-mpls-path-segment"/>. The PSID can be used for
      an associated bidirectional SR Path for identifying the SR Path.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>. The reader is assumed to be
      familiar with the terminology defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref
      target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="RFC8281"/>, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="PCEP Extension for Bidirectional SR Path">
      <t>As per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>, LSPs are
      associated by adding them to a common association group. <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> specifies PCEP extensions for
      grouping two reverse unidirectional MPLS-TE LSPs into an Associated
      Bidirectional LSP for both single-sided and double-sided initiation
      cases by defining two new Bidirectional LSP Association Groups.</t>

      <t>This document extends the procedure for associated bidirectional SR
      Paths by defining a new bidirectional association group (Double-sided
      Bidirectional SR Path Association Group). The document further describes
      the mechanism for associating two unidirectional SR Paths into a
      bidirectional SR Path. <xref target="I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment"/>
      defines a procedure for communicating Path Segment in PCEP for SR using
      PATH-SEGMENT TLV. The bidirectional SR Path can also use the
      PATH-SEGMENT TLV.</t>

      <t>Note that an association group is defined in this document to define
      procedures specific to SR Paths (and the procedures are different than
      the RSVP-TE bidirectional association groups defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>).</t>

      <section anchor="double-sided"
               title="Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path Association Group Object">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, two
        LSPs are associated as a bidirectional MPLS-TE LSP by a common
        bidirectional LSP association group. For associating two SR paths,
        this document defines a new association group called 'Double-sided
        Bidirectional SR Path Association Group' as follows: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Association Type (TBD1 to be assigned by IANA) = Double-sided
            Bidirectional SR Path Association Group</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Similar to other bidirectional associations, this Association Type
        is operator-configured in nature and statically created by the
        operator on the PCEP peers. The paths belonging to this association is
        conveyed via PCEP messages to the PCEP peer. Operator-configured
        Association Range TLV <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>
        MUST NOT be sent for these Association Types, and MUST be ignored, so
        that the entire range of association ID can be used for them. The
        handling of the Association ID, Association Source, optional Global
        Association Source and optional Extended Association ID in this
        association are set in the same way as <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>

        <t>A member of the 'Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path Association
        Group' can take the role of a forward or reverse SR Path and follow
        the similar rules defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> for LSPs.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>An SR Path (forward or reverse) can not be part of more than
            one 'Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path Association Group'.</t>

            <t>The endpoints of the SR Paths in this associations cannot be
            different.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>For describing the SR Paths in this association group, such as
        direction and co-routed information, this association group reuses the
        Bidirectional LSP Association Group TLV defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>. All fields and processing
        rules are as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Bidirectional Flag">
      <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, the B-flag in RP object MUST
      be set when the PCC specifies that the path computation request relates
      to a bidirectional TE LSP. In this document, the B-flag also MUST be set
      when the PCC specifies that the path computation request relates to a
      bidirectional SR Path. When a stateful PCE initiates or updates a
      bidirectional SR Paths including LSPs and SR paths, the B-flag in SRP
      object <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-stateful-pce-gmpls"/> MAY be set
      as well.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Procedures for Associated Bidirectional SR Path Computation">
      <t>Two unidirectional SR Paths can be associated by the association
      group object as specified in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>. A bidirectional LSP
      association group object is defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> (for MPLS-TE). This document
      extends these association mechanisms for bidirectional SR Paths. Two SR
      Paths can be associated together by using the Bidirectional SR Path
      Association Group defined in this document for PCEP messages. The
      PATH-SEGMENT TLV <xref target="I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment"/> SHOULD also
      be included in the LSP object for these SR Paths to support required
      use-cases.</t>

      <t>For bidirectional SR Paths, there is a need to know the reverse
      direction SR paths. The PCE SHOULD inform the reverse SR Paths to the
      ingress PCCs and vice versa. To achieve this, a PCInitiate message for
      the reverse SR Path is sent to the ingress PCC and a PCInitiate message
      for the forward SR Path is sent to the egress PCC (with the same
      association group). These PCInitiate message MUST NOT trigger initiation
      of SR Paths. The reverse direction SR Path can be used for several
      use-cases, such as directed BFD <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed"/>.</t>

      <t>For a bidirectional LSP computation when using both direction LSPs on
      a node, the same LSP would need to be identified using 2 different
      PLSP-IDs based on the PCEP session to the ingress or the egress. In
      other words, the LSP will have a PLSP-ID A at the ingress node while it
      will have the PLSP-ID B at the egress node. The PCE will maintain the
      two PLSP-IDs for the same LSP. For instance, an ingress PCC requests a
      bidirectional SR Path computation, and the PCE computes a forward LSP1
      with PLSP-ID say 100. The reverse LSP2 from the egress to the ingress
      with PLSP-ID say 200 is allocated by the egress PCC. Since the PLSP-ID
      space is independent at each PCC, the PLSP-ID allocated by the egress
      PCC can not be used for the LSP at the ingress PCC (PLSP-ID conflict may
      occur). Hence, the PCE needs to allocate a PLSP-ID for LSP2 from the
      ingress PCC's PLSP-ID space , say 101. Similarly for LSP1, it has
      PLSP-ID 100 at the ingress, and may have say PLSP-ID 201 at the egress
      node.</t>

      <!--<t>After path computation, the bidirectional path that combined by two
      SR paths and associated by an association group object will be sent to
      the source and destination PCC( as known as the ingress node and egress
      node in SR) by PCRep or PCUdp or PCInitiate messages, respectively. </t>-->

      <!--<t>A PCEP message such as PCRep or PCUdp or PCInitiate, containing a
      bidirectional path, sent to the PCC contains a forward direction path
      beginning from itself to the remote PCC and a reverse path from the
      remote PCC back to the PCC itself. The information of reverse direction
      path can be used for several scenarios, such as directed BFD <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed"/>.</t>-->

      <section title="PCE Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR Paths">
        <t>As specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>,
        Bidirectional SR Path Association Group can be created by a Stateful
        PCE.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Stateful PCE can create and update the forward and reverse SR
            Paths independently for a 'Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path
            Association Group'.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can establish and remove the association
            relationship on a per SR Path basis.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can create and update the SR Path and the
            association on a PCC via PCInitiate and PCUpd messages,
            respectively, using the procedures described in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>

            <t>The PATH-SEGMENT TLV SHOULD be included for each SR Path in the
            LSP object.</t>

            <t>The reverse direction SR Path (LSP2(R) at node S, LSP1(R) at
            node D) SHOULD be informed by PCE via PCInitiate message with the
            matching association group.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[                               +-----+
                               | PCE |
                               +-----+
   PCInitiate/PCUpd:           /     \         PCInitiate/PCUpd:
   Tunnel 1 (F)               /       \        Tunnel 2 (F)
   (LSP1 (F), LSP2 (R))      /         \       (LSP2 (F), LSP1 (R))
   Association #1           /           \      Association #1
                           /             \
                          v               v
                     +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                     |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                     |     |<------------|     |
                     +-----+    LSP2     +-----+
                           <no signaling>

      Figure 1: PCE-Initiated Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path
                with Forward and Reverse Direction SR Paths
           
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="PCC Initiated Associated Bidirectional SR Paths">
        <t>As specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>,
        Bidirectional SR Path Association Group can also be created by a
        PCC.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>PCC can create and update the forward and reverse SR Paths
            independently for a 'Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path
            Association Group'.</t>

            <t>PCC can establish and remove the association relationship on a
            per SR Path basis.</t>

            <t>PCC MUST report the change in the association group of an SR
            Path to PCE(s) via PCRpt message.</t>

            <t>PCC can report the forward and reverse SR Paths independently
            to PCE(s) via PCRpt message.</t>

            <t>PCC can delegate the forward and reverse SR Paths independently
            to a Stateful PCE, where PCE would control the SR Paths.</t>

            <t>Stateful PCE can update the SR Paths in the 'Double-sided
            Bidirectional SR Path Association Group' via PCUpd message, using
            the procedures described in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>.</t>

            <t>The PATH-SEGMENT TLV MUST be handled as defined in <xref
            target="I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment"/>.</t>

            <t>The reverse direction SR Path (LSP2(R) at node S, LSP1(R) at
            node D) SHOULD be informed by PCE via PCInitiate message with the
            matching association group.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                              +-----+
                              | PCE |
                              +-----+
   Report/Delegate:           ^     ^          Report/Delegate:
   Tunnel 1 (F)              /       \         Tunnel 2 (F)
   (LSP1 (F))               /         \        (LSP2 (F))
   Association #2          /           \       Association #2
                          /             \
                         /               \
                    +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                    |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                    |     |<------------|     |
                    +-----+    LSP2     +-----+
                          <no signaling>

     Figure 2a: Step 1: PCC-Initiated Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path
                with Forward Direction SR Paths


                               +-----+
                               | PCE |
                               +-----+
   PCUpd/PCInitiate:           /     \         PCUpd/PCInitiate:
   Tunnel 1 (F)               /       \        Tunnel 2 (F)
   (LSP1 (F), LSP2 (R))      /         \       (LSP2 (F), LSP1 (R))
   Association #2           /           \      Association #2
                           /             \
                          v               v
                     +-----+    LSP1     +-----+
                     |  S  |------------>|  D  |
                     |     |<------------|     |
                     +-----+    LSP2     +-----+
                           <no signaling>

   Figure 2b: Step 2: PCE-Upd/Initiated Double-sided Bidirectional Path
              Along with Reverse Direction SR Paths

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <!--<section title="Stateless PCE">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/>, for
        a stateless PCE, it might be useful to associate a path computation
        request to an association group, thus enabling it to associate a
        common set of configuration parameters or behaviors with the request.
        A PCC can request co-routed or non co-routed forward and reverse
        direction paths from a stateless PCE for a bidirectional LSP
        association group.</t>
      </section>-->

      <section title="Error Handling">
        <t>The error handling as described in section 5.5 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir"/> continue to apply.</t>

        <t>The PCEP Path Setup Type (PST) MUST be set to 'TE Path is Setup
        using Segment Routing' <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>
        for the LSP belonging to the 'Double-sided Bidirectional SR Path
        Association Group'. In case a PCEP speaker receives a different PST
        value for this association group, it MUST send a PCErr message with
        Error-Type = 29 (Early allocation by IANA) (Association Error) and
        Error-Value = TBD2 (Bidirectional LSP Association - Path Setup Type
        Mismatch).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Status">
      <t>[Note to the RFC Editor - remove this section before publication, as
      well as remove the reference to <xref target="RFC7942"/>.</t>

      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the
      protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this
      Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in <xref
      target="RFC7942"/>. The description of implementations in this section
      is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing
      drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any individual
      implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF. Furthermore,
      no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that
      was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not intended as, and must not
      be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their
      features. Readers are advised to note that other implementations may
      exist.</t>

      <t>According to <xref target="RFC7942"/>, "this will allow reviewers and
      working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the
      benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable
      experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols
      more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use this
      information as they see fit".</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Huawei's Commercial Delivery">
        <t>The feature is developing based on Huawei VRP8.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Organization: Huawei</t>

            <t>Implementation: Huawei's Commercial Delivery implementation
            based on VRP8.</t>

            <t>Description: The implementation is under development.</t>

            <t>Maturity Level: Product</t>

            <t>Contact: tanren@huawei.com</t>
          </list></t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="ZTE's Commercial Delivery">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Organization: ZTE</t>

            <t>Implementation: ZTE's Commercial Delivery implementation based
            on Rosng v8.</t>

            <t>Description: The implementation is under development.</t>

            <t>Maturity Level: Product</t>

            <t>Contact: zhan.shuangping@zte.com.cn</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t/>

      <section title="Association Type">
        <t>This document defines a new Association Type for the Association
        Object defined <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>. IANA
        is requested to make the assignment of a value for the sub-registry
        "ASSOCIATION Type Field" (to be created in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/>), as follows:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[   
Value  Name                                          Reference
-------------------------------------------------------------------
TBD1   Double-sided Bidirectional                    This document
       SR Path Association Group 

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="PCEP Errors">
        <t>This document defines new Error value for Error Type 29
        (Association Error). IANA is requested to allocate new Error value
        within the "PCEP-ERROR Object Error Types and Values" sub-registry of
        the PCEP Numbers registry, as follows:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Error Type  Description                              Reference
-------------------------------------------------------------------
 29         Association Error

            Error value: TBD2                        This document
            Bidirectional LSP Association -
            Path Setup Type Mismatch
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5440"/>,
      <xref target="RFC8231"/>, <xref target="RFC8281"/>, and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> apply to the extensions defined
      in this document as well.</t>

      <t>A new Association Type for the Association Object, 'Double-sided
      Associated Bidirectional SR Path Association Group' is introduced in
      this document. Additional security considerations related to LSP
      associations due to a malicious PCEP speaker is described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pce-association-group"/> and apply to this Association
      Type. Hence, securing the PCEP session using Transport Layer Security
      (TLS) <xref target="RFC8253"/> is recommended.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Manage" title="Manageability Considerations">
      <t>All manageability requirements and considerations listed in <xref
      target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
      target="RFC8281"/> apply to PCEP protocol extensions defined in this
      document. In addition, requirements and considerations listed in this
      section apply.</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Control of Function and Policy">
        <t>The mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any control or
        policy requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref
        target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
        target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Information and Data Models">
        <t><xref target="RFC7420"/> describes the PCEP MIB, there are no new
        MIB Objects defined for Bidirectional SR Path associations. The PCEP
        YANG module <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang"/> defines data model
        for Bidirectional SR Path associations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Liveness Detection and Monitoring">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new liveness
        detection and monitoring requirements in addition to those already
        listed in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and
        <xref target="RFC8281"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Verify Correct Operations">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new operation
        verification requirements in addition to those already listed in <xref
        target="RFC5440"/>, <xref target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/> .</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements On Other Protocols">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in this document do not imply any new
        requirements on other protocols.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact On Network Operations">
        <t>Mechanisms defined in <xref target="RFC5440"/>, <xref
        target="RFC8231"/>, and <xref target="I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing"/>
        also apply to PCEP extensions defined in this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>The following people have substantially contributed to this
      document:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[    Dhruv Dhody
    Huawei Technologies
    Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield
    Bangalore, Karnataka  560066
    India

    Email: dhruv.ietf@gmail.com

    Zhenbin Li
    Huawei Technologies
    Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
    Beijing  100095
    China

    Email: lizhenbin@huawei.com


    Jie Dong
    Huawei Technologies
    Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Rd.
    Beijing  100095
    China

    Email: jie.dong@huawei.com


]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Many thanks to Marina Fizgeer for detailed review and comments.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8231'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8281"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-group'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-association-bidir'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-stateful-pce-gmpls'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.li-pce-sr-path-segment'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4657'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8253"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8402'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7942'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7420'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-segment-routing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-bfd-directed'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-spring-mpls-path-segment'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pce-pcep-yang'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
